Guide to the Department of Geology and Geophysics, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Department of Geology and Geophysics, Yale University, records
1789-1957
RU 426
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.5
(11 boxes)
The records consist of correspondence, memoranda, subject files, minutes, grade books of Richard Foster Flint, and a departmental history documenting the activities and operations of the Yale Department of Geology and Geophysics. Includes mineralogy papers and notebooks of Yale mineralogists Samuel Lewis Penfield, George Jarvis Brush and William Ebenezer Ford. The records also include correspondence relating to Yale's acquisition of Baron Lederer's mineral cabinet.
Yale University. Department of Geology and Geophysics
Brush, George Jarvis, 1831-1912
Flint, Richard Foster, 1902-1976
Ford, William E. (William Ebenezer), 1878-1939
Penfield, Samuel Lewis, 1856-1906
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 14-B (YRG 14-B), Records of academic departments and programs of the Yale Faculty of Arts and Sciences.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, memoranda, subject files, minutes, grade books of Richard Foster Flint, and a departmental history documenting the activities and operations of the Yale Department of Geology and Geophysics. Includes mineralogy papers and notebooks of Yale mineralogists Samuel Lewis Penfield, George Jarvis Brush and William Ebenezer Ford. The records also include correspondence relating to Yale's acquisition of Baron Lederer's mineral cabinet.
Geology -- Research; Geology -- Study and teaching; Mineralogy -- Research; Mineralogy -- Study and teaching; Minerals -- Collection and preservation; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Departments; Grade books; Dana, Edward Salisbury, 1849-1935; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Department of Geology and Geophysics
- Records, 1901-1908; Accession 1935-A-001
  - "History of the Geological Department at Yale University" HEG (Box 1, Folder 1 - 3)
  - Correspondence, 1901-1908, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Proposed expedition to Patagonia, 1905? (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Printed material (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Minutes of faculty meetings and mineralogical papers, 1789-1957; Accession 1958-A-001
  - Mineralogical correspondence to:
    - Dana, Edward Salisbury, 1878-1894 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dana, Edward Salisbury, 1895-1897 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dana, Edward Salisbury, 1898-1934 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Dana, James Dwight, 1851-1867 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dana, James Dwight, 1868-1876 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dana, James Dwight, 1877-1878 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dana, James Dwight, 1879-1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Ford, William Ebenezer, 1911-1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Penfield, Samuel Lewis, 1891-1900 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Shepard, Charles Upham, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, 1842-1843 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, 1843 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, 1843 August - 1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Notes of Benjamin Silliman on acquisition of Baron Lederer's Cabinet, 1843 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Undated and miscellaneous correspondence (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mineralogical lists, catalogues and papers
    - Details of the fall of meteoric iron in the district of Agram in upper Sclavonia, 1751 May 26, 1789 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Original catalogue of the mineral collection of George Brush, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Contributors to the Brush Collection, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous mineralogical materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Lista di 352 Exempari di Minerali", undated (Box 1A, Folder 19)
    - "Erstes Hundert Einer... Mineralien Samlung von Ungern fur Herrn W. Gibbs... Professor E. A. Zipser...", undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "Catalogue d'une Collection de Fossils Principalement du St. Gotham et du Wally" by Porfessors Struve and Lausanne, bound with "Substance's Minerales Nouvelles", undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Catalogue of North American Minerals" 3 vols. Author unknown, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Plan of the Mineralogical and Geological Cabinet in Yale College, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mineralogical notebooks
    - Brush, George Jarvis (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - "Bibliography of American Minerals", 1852 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "Swansea, South Wales", 1856 May (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Account book, 1856-1862 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous notebook [George J. Brush?], undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous notebook [George J. Brush?], undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous notebook [George J. Brush?], undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Stereographic scales [George J. Brush?], undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Miles, D. A.
    - Untitled, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Penfield, Samuel Lewis
    - "Rosenbusch, Crystallography" v. 1, 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - "Descriptive Mineralogy, V. I and II, Rosenbusch", undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - "Mineralogy", undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - "Quantitative Chemistry", undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - "Mineralogical Formulae", undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - "Heidelberg", 1884 May (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - "Blowpipe Analysis", 1879 September (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - "Quantitative Analysis", undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Minutes of the Faculty, Dept. of Geology
    - Vol. I 1908-1919 (Box 6)
    - Vol. II 1919-1932 (Box 7)
    - Vol. III 1932-1949 (Box 7)
    - Vol. IV 1950-1957 (Box 7)
  - Mineral Cabinet
    - Correspondence, 1825-1843 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - Correspondence, 1849-1857 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - Correspondence, 1865-1883 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - List of contents, undated (Box 8, Folder 60)
- Grade books, 1925-1942; Accession 1977-A-002
  - Grade Books of Foster Flint
    - 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1926-1927, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1928-1929, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1930-1931, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Chester R. Longwell]
    - 1932-1933, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1933-1934, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1935-1936, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1937-1938, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1939-1940, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Division 1, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Division 2, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - A - K, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - L - Z, 1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)